<idea-plugin>
    <id>com.datapreprocessor.plugin</id>
    <name>Data Preprocessor</name>
    <version>1.8.2</version>
    <vendor email="admin@keencodelabs.com" url="https://github.com/codaBlurd/data-preprocessor-plugin">
        Keen Code Labs
    </vendor>
    <product-descriptor code="PDATAPREPROCESS" release-date="20260610" release-version="18" optional="true"/>

    <description><![CDATA[
        <p>Stop writing repetitive pandas preprocessing scripts.</p>

        <p><b>Data Preprocessor</b> is an in-IDE toolkit for cleaning, transforming, and preparing datasets
        directly inside your JetBrains IDE.</p>

        <p>Load a <b>CSV, Excel (.xlsx), or JSON</b> file, profile your data instantly, handle missing values,
        remove duplicates and outliers, normalize columns, and generate ready-to-run <b>Python (pandas)</b>
        code from your workflow. Pro unlocks <b>R</b> and <b>SQL</b> generation, reusable pipelines,
        column visualisations, custom regex rules, and batch processing — all without leaving the IDE.</p>

        <b>Key features:</b>
        <ul>
          <li><b>Column Profiling &amp; Statistics</b> — type, null count, unique count, mean, median, std dev, min, max, mode</li>
          <li><b>Missing Value Handling</b> — drop rows or fill with mean, median, mode, or a custom value</li>
          <li><b>Duplicate Removal</b> — detect and remove duplicate rows in one click</li>
          <li><b>Outlier Detection (IQR)</b> — identify and remove outliers using the IQR fence method</li>
          <li><b>Data Normalization</b> — Min-Max scaling [0, 1], Z-Score standardisation (mean=0, std=1), or Robust Scaler (median/IQR)</li>
          <li><b>Column Type Casting</b> — cast any column to int, float, boolean, or string</li>
          <li><b>Label Encoding</b> — encode categorical columns to integer indices</li>
          <li><b>One-Hot Encoding</b> — expand categorical columns into binary dummy columns</li>
          <li><b>Train / Test Split</b> — split the dataset with a configurable ratio; reflected in generated Python and Pro R code</li>
          <li><b>Sort Column</b> — sort the dataset ascending or descending by any column (numeric or text)</li>
          <li><b>Filter Rows</b> — keep only rows matching a condition (==, !=, &gt;, &lt;, &gt;=, &lt;=, contains)</li>
          <li><b>Regex Replace [Pro]</b> — clean text columns with custom regex find/replace rules, including capture-group replacements</li>
          <li><b>Reusable Pipelines [Pro]</b> — import/export cleaning pipelines as `.dpp` JSON files</li>
          <li><b>Multi-File Batch Mode [Pro]</b> — apply the current pipeline to many CSV, Excel, or JSON files and export cleaned CSV copies</li>
          <li><b>Python Code Generation</b> — one click produces a complete, ready-to-run pandas script</li>
          <li><b>R Code Generation [Pro]</b> — one click produces an equivalent base-R script; readxl / jsonlite / fastDummies imported only when needed</li>
          <li><b>SQL Code Generation [Pro]</b> — one click produces a PostgreSQL-style CTE template for database-side preprocessing</li>
          <li><b>Undo / Redo</b> — step back and forward through pipeline edits without losing work</li>
          <li><b>Export cleaned CSV</b> — choose where to save the transformed dataset via a file dialog</li>
          <li><b>Copy cleaned data as TSV</b> — paste applied results directly into Excel or Google Sheets</li>
          <li><b>Column Visualisations [Pro]</b> — histogram and box plot per numeric column rendered inside the tool window; charts update automatically after Apply</li>
          <li><b>Settings</b> — configure preview row limit, default normalization method, and default train/test ratio</li>
        </ul>

        <p>Built for <b>data scientists, analysts, and developers</b> who want faster preprocessing
        without leaving their IDE.</p>

        <p>Compatible with <b>IntelliJ IDEA</b>, <b>PyCharm</b>, <b>DataGrip</b>, and other JetBrains IDEs.</p>

        <br/>
        <b>Privacy:</b> This plugin does not collect, store, or transmit any user data.
        All processing is performed locally within the IDE.
    ]]></description>

    <depends>com.intellij.modules.platform</depends>

    <extensions defaultExtensionNs="com.intellij">
        <toolWindow
                id="Data Preprocessor"
                secondary="false"
                anchor="right"
                factoryClass="com.datapreprocessor.toolwindow.DataPreprocessorToolWindowFactory"
                icon="/icons/dataPreprocessor.svg"/>

        <notificationGroup
                id="DataPreprocessor.Notifications"
                displayType="BALLOON"/>

        <applicationService
                serviceImplementation="com.datapreprocessor.settings.DataPreprocessorSettings"/>

        <applicationConfigurable
                parentId="tools"
                instance="com.datapreprocessor.settings.DataPreprocessorConfigurable"
                id="com.datapreprocessor.settings"
                displayName="Data Preprocessor"/>
    </extensions>

    <actions>
        <group id="DataPreprocessor.ContextMenu"
               text="Data Preprocessor"
               popup="true">
            <add-to-group group-id="ProjectViewPopupMenu" anchor="last"/>

            <action id="DataPreprocessor.OpenFile"
                    class="com.datapreprocessor.actions.OpenDataFileAction"
                    text="Open in Data Preprocessor"
                    description="Load this data file into the Data Preprocessor tool window"/>

            <action id="DataPreprocessor.GenerateCode"
                    class="com.datapreprocessor.actions.GeneratePreprocessingCodeAction"
                    text="Generate Preprocessing Code"
                    description="Insert generated pandas preprocessing code at the caret"/>
        </group>

        <group id="DataPreprocessor.ToolsMenu">
            <add-to-group group-id="ToolsMenu" anchor="last"/>
            <action id="DataPreprocessor.OpenTool"
                    class="com.datapreprocessor.actions.OpenToolWindowAction"
                    text="Open Data Preprocessor…"
                    description="Open the Data Preprocessor tool window"/>
        </group>
    </actions>
</idea-plugin>
